There's an old joke.
Two elderly women are at
a Catskill mountain resort.
One says, "The food at this
place is really terrible. "
The other says, "I know,
and such small portions. "
That's essentially
how I feel about life:
full of loneliness, misery,
suffering and unhappiness...
and it's all over
much too quickly.
The other important
joke for me...
is one usually attributed
to Groucho Marx...
but it appears originally in Freud's
Wit and Its Relation to the Unconscious.
It goes like this,
I'm paraphrasing:
I never want to belong to any club that
would have someone like me for a member.
That's the key joke of my adult life
in terms of my relationships with women.
Lately the strangest things have
been going through my mind...
because I turned 40, and I guess
I'm going through a life crisis.
I'm not worried about aging.
I'm not one of those characters.
But I'm balding slightly on top. That's
about the worst you can say about me.
I think I'm going to get
better as I get older.
I think I'm going to be
the balding, virile type...
as opposed to the
distinguished gray.
Unless I'm neither of those two.
Unless I'm one of those guys with
saliva dribbling out of his mouth...
who wanders into a cafeteria with a
shopping bag, screaming about socialism.
Annie and I broke up, and I still
can't get my mind around that.
I keep sifting the pieces of the
relationship through my mind...
examining my life and trying to
figure out where did the screw-up come.
A year ago we were in love.
It's funny. I'm not a morose type.
I'm not a depressive character.
I was a reasonably happy kid.
I was brought up in
Brooklyn during World War ll.
He's been depressed.
- Suddenly he can't do anything.
- Why are you depressed, Alvy?
Tell Dr. Flicker.
It's something he read.
Something he read, huh?
- The universe is expanding.
- The universe is expanding?
The universe is everything,
and if it's expanding...
someday it will break apart, and
that will be the end of everything.
What is that your business?
He stopped doing his homework!
- What's the point?
- What's the universe got to do with it?
You're here in Brooklyn.
Brooklyn is not expanding!
It won't be expanding
for billions of years!
We've got to try and enjoy
ourselves while we're here! Huh?
My analyst says I exaggerate
my childhood memories...
but I swear I was brought up
underneath the roller coaster...
in the Coney Island
section of Brooklyn.
Maybe that accounts for my
personality, which is a little nervous.
I have a hyperactive imagination. My
mind tends to jump around a little.
I have some trouble
between fantasy and reality.
My father ran the
bumper-car concession.
There he is, and there I am.
I used to get my aggression
out through those cars.
I remember the staff
at our public school.
We had a saying, "Those
who can't do, teach...
and those who can't
teach, teach gym. "
And those who couldn't do anything,
I think, were assigned to our school.
I must say, I always thought
my schoolmates were idiots.
Melvyn Greenglass and
his fat little face.
And Henrietta Farrell,
Miss Perfect all the time.
And Ivan Ackerman, always
the wrong answer. Always!
Seven and three is nine.
Even then I knew
they were just jerks.
In 1942 I had already
discovered women.
He kissed me!
That's the second time
this month! Step up here.
- What did I do?
- Step up here.
- You should be ashamed of yourself.
Why? I was just expressing
a healthy sexual curiosity.
Six-year-old boys don't
have girls on their minds.
I did.
For God sakes, Alvy, even Freud
speaks of a latency period!
I never had a latency
period. I can't help it.
Why couldn't you have
been more like Donald?
There was a model boy.
Tell the folks where
you are today, Donald.
I run a profitable dress company.
Sometimes I wonder where
my classmates are today.
I'm president of the
Pinkus Plumbing Company.
I sell talliths.
I used to be a heroin addict,
now I'm a methadone addict.
I'm into leather.
I lost track of most of my old
schoolmates, but I wound up a comedian.
They did not take me in the army.
I was 4-P.
In the event of
war, I'm a hostage.
You always only saw
the worst in people.
You never could get along
with anyone in school.
You were always out
of step with the world.
Even when you got famous, you
still distrusted the world.
I distinctly heard it. He
muttered under his breath, "Jew. "
- You're crazy.
- No, I'm not.
We were walking off the tennis court.
He was there and me and his wife.
He looked her, then
they both looked at me...
and under his breath
he said, "Jew. "
You're a total paranoid.
How am I a paranoid? I pick
up on those kind of things.
I was having lunch with guys from
NBC, so I said, "Did you eat yet?"
Tom Christie said, "No.
Jew?" Not "Did you?"
Not "Did you eat?" but
"Jew eat?" You get it?
- Max- - Stop
calling me Max.
Why? It's a good name for you. Max,
you see conspiracies in everything.
No, I don't. I was in a
record store. Listen to this.
There's this tall, blond crew-cutted guy
and he's looking at me in a funny way.
He's saying, "Yes, we have
a sale this week on Wagner. "
Wagner, Max. I know what
he's trying to tell me.
Very significantly, Wagner.
Right, Max. California, Max.
- Get the hell out of this crazy city.
- Forget it.
We move to sunny L.A. All of
show business is out there.
You keep bringing it up, but I
don't want to live in a city...
where the only cultural advantage is
you can make a right turn on a red light.
All right, forget it. Aren't you
going to be late for meeting Annie?
I'm meeting her in front of the Beekman.
I have a few minutes left, right?
Are you on television?
Yeah, occasionally.
What's your name?
You wouldn't know
it. It doesn't matter.
You're on Johnny Carson, right?
Once in a while.
What's your name?
- I'm Robert Redford.
- Come on!
Alvy Singer. Thanks
very much for everything.
This is Alvy Singer!
This guy's on television.
Alvy Singer, right? Am I right?
- Give me a break.
- This guy's on television.
I need the large polo mallet.
- Who's on television?
- This guy, on the Johnny Carson Show.
- Is this a meeting of the teamsters?
- What program?
- Can I have your autograph?
- You don't want my autograph.
I do! It's for my girlfriend.
Make it out to Ralph.
- Your girlfriend's name is Ralph?
- It's for my brother.
You're really Alvy
Singer, the TV star?
- Alvy Singer over here!
- It's all right, fellas.
Jesus, what did you do? Come
by way of the Panama Canal?
- I'm in a bad mood.
- I'm here with the Godfather cast.
- Learn to deal with it.
- I'm dealing with two guys named Cheech.
Please, I have a headache.
You are in a bad mood. You
must be getting your period.
I'm not getting my period! Jesus!
Every time anything out of the ordinary
happens, you think I have my period.
A little louder. I think one
of them may have missed it.
- Has the picture started?
- Two minutes ago.
That's it. Forget
it. I can't go in.
- Two minutes.
- We've blown it already.
I can't go in, in the middle.
In the middle? We've only missed
the titles. They're in Swedish.
You want to get
coffee for two hours?
- Two hours? No. I'm going
in. - Go ahead. Good-bye.
While we're talking,
we could be inside.
Can we not argue in front of
everybody? I get embarrassed.
- All right. So what do you want to do?
- I don't know. Go to another movie?
- Let's see The Sorrow and the Pity.
- We've seen it.
I'm not in the mood to see a
four hour documentary on Nazis.
I'm sorry.
I've got to see a picture exactly
from start to finish, 'cause I'm anal.
That's a polite word
for what you are.
We saw the Fellini film last
Tuesday. It is not one of his best.
It lacks a cohesive structure.
You get the feeling he's not absolutely
sure what it is he wants to say.
I've always felt he was
essentially a technical filmmaker.
Granted La Strada
was a great film.
Great in its use of negative
imagery more than anything else.
- I'm going to have a stroke.
- Stop listening to him.
He's screaming his
opinions in my ear.
All that Juliet of the
Spirits or Satyricon.
I found it incredibly indulgent.
He really is one of the
most indulgent of filmmakers.
Key word here is "indulgent. "
- What are you depressed about?
- I missed my therapy. I overslept.
How can you possibly oversleep?
The alarm clock.
You know what a hostile
gesture that is to me?
I know. Because of our
sexual problem, right?
Everybody in line has to
know our rate of intercourse?
It's like Samuel Beckett.
I admire the technique, but it
doesn't hit me on a gut level.
- I'd like to hit him on a gut level.
- Stop it.
He's spitting on my
neck when he talks.
You know something else?
You're so egocentric that...
if I miss my therapy you can only think
of it in terms of how it affects you!
They're probably
on their first date.
Probably met by answering an ad
in the New York Review of Books.
"Thirtyish academic
wishes to meet woman...
who's interested in Mozart,
James Joyce and sodomy. "
What do you mean
"our sexual problem"?
I'm comparatively normal
for a guy raised in Brooklyn.
I'm sorry. My sexual problem.
Okay? My sexual problem!
I never read that. That was Henry
James' sequel to Turn of the Screw?
It's the influence of television.
Marshall McLuhan deals with it in
terms of it being a high intensity.
Do you understand? A hot medium.
What I wouldn't give for a large
sock with horse manure in it.
What do you do when you get stuck
on a movie line with a guy like this?
Wait. Why can't I give my
opinion? It's a free country!
He can. Do you have
to give it so loud?
Aren't you ashamed to
pontificate like that?
The funny part is, you don't know
anything about Marshall McLuhan.
I happen to teach a class at Columbia
called "TV, Media and Culture. "
I think my insights into Mr. McLuhan
have a great deal of validity.
Do you? That's funny, because I
happen to have Mr. McLuhan right here.
Just let me
- Come over here. Tell him.
I heard what you were saying.
You know nothing of my work. You
mean my whole fallacy is wrong.
How you ever got to teach a course
in anything is totally amazing!
If life were only like this.
June 14, 1940. The German
army occupies Paris.
All over the country, people
are desperate for food.
Those guys in the French
Resistance were really brave.
To have to listen to Maurice
Chevalier sing so much.
I know. Sometimes I ask myself
how I'd stand up under torture.
You? You kidding?
The Gestapo would take away your charge
card, and you'd tell 'em everything.
That movie makes me feel guilty.
It's supposed to.
- Alvy,
I- - What?
What's the matter?
It's not natural. We're
sleeping in a bed together.
It's been a long time!
It's just, I mean-
I've got to sing tomorrow night,
so I have to rest my voice.
It's always some kind of an excuse.
You used to think I was very sexy.
When we first started going
out, we had sex constantly.
We're probably listed in The
Guiness Book of World Records.
It'll pass. I'm going
through a phase, that's all.
You've been married before.
You know how things can get.
You were very hot
for Allison at first.
You know that you're on right after
Chris Brown, in about 20 minutes.
Excuse me. When do I go on?
Who are you?
Alvy Singer.
- I'm the comedian.
- Oh, comedian.
Oh, you're on next.
What do you mean "next"?
You're on right after this act.
- It can't be, because he's a comic.
- Yes.
- You're putting on two comics in a row?
- Why not?
No, I'm sorry. I'm not going
to go on after another comedian.
- It's okay.
- No. They're laughing. I'd rather not.
Will you relax, please?
They're going to love you.
I know. I prefer not to.
Look, they're laughing at him.
What are you telling me? They'll
laugh at him a few minutes.
Then I've got to get laughs,
too. How much can they laugh?
- They're laughed out.
- Do you feel all right?
Jesus.
- What's your name?
- Allison.
Yeah? Allison what?
Portchnik.
- Portchnik? That's nice.
- Thank you.
So, you work for
Stevenson all the time?
- No. I'm doing my thesis.
- On what?
Political commitment in
20th-century literature.
You're like New York Jewish,
left-wing, intellectual...
Central Park West, Brandeis
University, socialist summer camps...
and the father with the
Ben Shahn drawings...
really
strike-oriented-
Stop me before I make a
complete imbecile of myself.
That was wonderful! I love being
reduced to a cultural stereotype.
Right. I'm a bigot,
but for the left.
I have to go out there. Say
something encouraging, quickly.
- I think you're cute.
- Yeah? Do you?
Go ahead.
I don't know why they would
have me at this kind of rally...
'cause I'm not essentially
a political comedian.
I interestingly
had dated a woman...
in the Eisenhower
administration, briefly.
It was ironic to me...
'cause I was trying
to do to her...
what Eisenhower's been doing to the
country for the last eight years.
I'm sorry. I can't
go through with this.
I can't get it off my
mind! It's obsessing me!
I'm getting tired of it.
I need your attention.
But it doesn't make any sense. He
drove past the book depository...
and the police said conclusively
that it was an exit wound.
So how is it possible for Oswald to
have fired from two angles at once?
It doesn't make sense!
I'll tell you this. He
was not marksman enough...
to hit a moving
target at that range.
But if there was
a second assassin-
- That's it!
- We've been through this.
They recovered the
shells from that rifle.
What are you saying now?
That everybody on the Warren Commission
is in on this conspiracy, right?
Why not?
- Earl Warren?
- Honey, I don't know Earl Warren.
Lyndon Johnson?
Lyndon Johnson is a politician!
You know the ethics those guys have.
It's a notch underneath child molester.
Then everybody's in
on the conspiracy.
The FBl and the CIA and J. Edgar
Hoover, the oil companies...
the Pentagon, the men's-room
attendant at the White House?
I would leave out the
men's-room attendant.
You're using this conspiracy theory
as an excuse to avoid sex with me.
Oh, my God! She's right.
Why did I turn off
Allison Portchnik?
She was beautiful. She was
willing. She was real intelligent.
Is it the old
Groucho Marx joke...
that I don't want to belong to any
club that would have me for a member?
- Alvy, don't panic!
- It's a mistake...
to bring a live
thing in the house.
Don't do that.
Maybe we should call the police.
Dial 911. It's the lobster squad.
They're only baby
ones. For God sakes.
- If they're babies, you pick them up.
- All right! All right!
- Here you go!
- Don't give it to me.
Look! One crawled
behind the refrigerator.
It'll turn up in our bed at night.
Get out of here with that thing!
Talk to him. You speak shellfish.
Hey, put it in the pot.
I can't. I can't put a
live thing in hot water.
What d'you think we were going
to do, take him to the movies?
Good. Oh, thank you.
Okay, it's in. It's
definitely in the pot.
Annie, there's a big lobster
behind the refrigerator.
I can't get it out.
This thing's heavy.
Maybe if I put a dish of butter sauce
here, it'll run out the other side.
I'm going to get my camera.
I think if I could pry-
We should have gotten steaks, 'cause
they don't have legs and run around.
- Pick this lobster up. Hold it, please.
- You're going to take pictures now?
Alvy, it'll be
wonderful. Oh, lovely!
- It's disgusting.
- One more, please? One more.
Good!
Here's what I want to know.
Am I your first, big romance?
- Who was?
- There was Dennis from high school.
Local kid who'd meet you in front
of the movie house on Saturday night?
- You should've seen how I looked then.
- I can imagine. An astronaut's wife.
- Then there was Jerry, the actor.
- Look at you.
You're such a clown.
- I look pretty.
- You always do. But that guy with you!
Acting is like an exploration
of the soul. It's very religious.
Like a kind of
liberating consciousness.
It's like a visual poem.
Is he kidding with that crap?
Oh, right!
Right. I think I know exactly what
you mean when you say "religious. "
- You do?
- Come on. I was younger.
That was last year!
It's like when I think of dying.
You know how I'd like to die?
How?
I'd like to get torn
apart by wild animals.
- Heavy! Eaten by some squirrels.
- He was a terrific actor.
He's neat looking
and he was emotional.
I don't think you
like emotion too much.
Touch my heart with your foot.
I may throw up.
- He was creepy.
- Yeah!
- You're pretty lucky I came
along. - Oh, really? La-de-dah!
If anyone ever told me that
I'd be taking out a girl...
who used expressions
like "la-de-dah"-
That's right. You really
like those New York girls.
- Not just. Not only.
- I'd say so. You married two of them.
There's Henry Drucker.
He has a Chair in
History at Princeton.
The short man is Hershel Kaminsky. He
has a Chair in Philosophy at Cornell.
Two more chairs, they
got a dining room set.
- Why are you so hostile?
- I want to watch the Knicks on TV.
Is that Paul Goodman? No.
Be nice to the host, because
he's publishing my book.
Hi, Doug. Douglas Wyeth...
The Foul Rag-and-Bone
Shop of the Heart.
I'm so tired of
spending evenings...
making fake insights with
people who work for Dysentery.
Commentary.
I heard Commentary and Dissent
had merged and formed Dysentery.
No jokes. These
are friends. Okay?
Cleveland Cavaliers losing
to the New York Knicks.
Here you are. There's
people out there.
Two minutes ago, the Knicks
are ahead 14 points...
and now they're ahead two points.
Alvy, what is so fascinating...
about a group of pituitary cases
trying to stuff a ball through a hoop?
What is fascinating
is that it's physical.
That's one thing
about intellectuals:
They've proved you can be brilliant
and have no idea what's going on.
But, on the other hand, the
body doesn't lie as we now know.
Stop acting out.
It'll be great, because all those
Ph. D.s are in there discussing...
modes of alienation, and we'll
be in here quietly humping.
Don't. You're using sex
to express hostility.
"Why do you always reduce my animal
urges to psychoanalytic categories,"...
he said as he
removed her brassier.
There are people out there
from the New Yorker magazine!
My God! What would they think?
- Damn siren!
- Don't get upset.
Damn it! I was so close!
Last night it was a guy
honking his car horn.
The city can't close down.
You want them to close the
airport so we can have sex?
I'm too tense. I need a Valium.
My analyst says I should live in
the country and not in New York.
We can't have this discussion all the
time. The country makes me nervous.
You've got crickets. It's quiet.
There's no place to walk after dinner.
There's the screens with
the dead moths behind them.
You got the Manson family,
possibly. You got Dick and Perry.
Okay! My analyst just thinks I'm too
tense! Where's the goddamn Valium?
Okay, it's quiet now.
We can get started again.
I can't! My head is throbbing.
- You got a headache?
- I have a headache!
- Bad?
- Like Oswald in Ghosts.
- Jesus.
- Where are you going?
I'm going to take another
in a series of cold showers.
Max, my serve is going to
send you to the showers early.
Right. To get back to
what we were discussing.
The failure of the country to get
behind New York City is anti-Semitism.
Max, the city is terribly run.
I'm not discussing politics
or economics. This is foreskin.
That's a convenient out. When some group
disagrees with you, it's anti-Semitism.
The rest of the country
looks upon New York...
like we're left-wing, communist,
Jewish, homosexual pornographers.
I think of us that way
sometimes, and I live here.
Max, if we lived in California, we
could play outdoors every day in the sun.
Sun is bad for you. Everything
our parents said was good is bad.
Sun, milk, red meat, college.
Egad, here he comes.
You know Alvy? This is Janet.
- This is Annie Hall.
- This is Alvy.
- Who's playing with who here?
- You and me against them?
- That's not fair.
- I can't play too good.
I've had four lessons.
Well...
bye.
- You play very well.
- Oh, yeah? So do you!
God, what a dumb thing to say.
You say "You play well," and right
away I have to say, "You play well. "
Oh, God, Annie.
Well. Oh, well!
La-de-dah.
You want a lift?
Oh, why? You got a car?
No, I was going to take a cab.
Oh, no. I have a car.
You have a car?
If you have a car...
then why did you say, "Do you
have a car" like you wanted a lift?
Geez, I don't know. I wasn't-
I got this VW out there.
What a jerk.
Would you like a lift?
- Sure. Which way are you going?
- Me? Oh, downtown.
I'm going uptown.
Oh, I'm going uptown, too.
- You said you were going
downtown. - Yeah, well-
I can go uptown,
too. I live uptown.
What the hell? It would be nice
having company. I hate driving alone.
How long do you know Janet?
Where do you know her from?
- I'm in her acting class.
- You're an actress!
Well, I do commercials, sort of.
You want to watch the road?
You're not from New York, right?
- Chippewa Falls.
- Right.
- Where?
- Wisconsin.
- You're driving a tad rapidly.
- Don't worry. I'm a very good driver.
- You want some gum?
- No, thanks.
- Where is it?
- Don't do that. No, no, watch the road.
I'll get it.
Concentrate, will ya?
- I'll get you a piece.
- Listen. You drive?
Do I drive? No, I got
a problem with driving.
- You do?
- Yeah.
I got a license, but I
have too much hostility.
Nice car. You keep it nice.
- Can I ask you, is this a sandwich?
- Oh, yeah.
I live over here. Oh, my God,
look! There's a parking space.
That's okay, we can walk
to the curb from here.
You want your tennis
stuff? You want your gear?
Yeah. That's good.
Thanks. Thanks a lot. Well.
Well.
- Thank you.
You're a wonderful
tennis player...
and you're the worst driver
I've ever seen in my life.
Anyplace. Europe. Anyplace. Asia.
- I love what you're wearing.
- You do? Yeah.
This tie is a present
from Grammy Hall.
Who? Grammy Hall?
Yeah, my grammy.
What did you do, grow up in a Norman
Rockwell painting? Your grammy?
- It's pretty silly, isn't it?
- My grammy never gave gifts.
She was too busy getting
raped by Cossacks.
Well, thank you again.
Oh, yeah.
Listen. You want to come upstairs
and have a glass of wine or something?
No, I mean you don't have to.
You're probably late and everything.
No, that would be fine.
I wouldn't mind. Sure.
I got time. I got nothing
until my analyst appointment.
You see an analyst?
- Just for 15 years.
- 15 years?
I'm going to give him one more
year, and then I'm going to Lourdes.
15? Nah, come on! Yeah? Really?
Sylvia Plath. Interesting
poetess whose tragic suicide...
was misinterpreted as romantic
by the college-girl mentality.
Right. I don't know. I mean,
some of her poems seem neat.
Neat? I hate to tell
you this is 1975.
"Neat" went out at the
turn of the century.
Who are those photos on the wall?
Oh, you see...
that's my dad, that's Father,
and that's my brother, Duane.
Yeah, right. And over
there's Grammy Hall.
- And that's Sadie.
- Who's Sadie?
Well, Sadie met Grammy through
Grammy's brother, George.
George was real sweet.
He had that thing.
What is that thing where you fall
asleep in the middle of a sentence?
- Narcolepsy.
- Right.
So anyway, George went to the
union to get his free turkey...
because the union always gave George
this free turkey at Christmastime...
because he was shell-shocked
in the first World War.
Anyway, so George is
standing in line...
getting his free turkey...
but the thing is he falls
asleep, and he never wakes up.
So he's dead.
He's dead. Yeah.
Oh, dear.
Well, terrible, huh?
Wouldn't you say?
Pretty awful.
It's a great story, though.
It really made my day.
I think I should get out of
here, 'cause I think I'm imposing.
Really? Maybe-
- You don't have to.
- But I'm all perspired and everything.
Didn't you take a
shower at the club?
No, no. I never shower
in a public place.
Why not?
I don't like to get naked
in front of another man.
I see.
I don't like to show my
body to a man of my gender.
- I see, I guess.
- You never know what's going to happen.
- 15 years, huh?
- 15 years, yeah.
God bless.
Well! Well-
You're what Grammy Hall
would call "a real Jew. "
Thank you.
She hates Jews. She thinks
they just make money.
But she's the one, is
she ever. I'm telling you.
So, did you do those
photographs in there?
I dabble? Listen to me. What a jerk.
Yeah, I sort of dabble around, you know.
You are a great-looking girl. They're
wonderful. They have a quality.
He probably thinks I'm a yo-yo. Well, I would
like to take a serious photography course.
Photography's
interesting because...
I wonder what she looks like naked. it's a new art
form. A set of aesthetic criteria have not emerged yet.
I'm not smart enough for him. Hang in there.
You mean whether it's a good photo or not?
I don't know what I'm saying. She senses I'm shallow. The
medium enters in as a condition of the art form itself.
God, I hope he doesn't turn out to be a schmuck like
the others. Well, to me- I mean- It's all instinctive.
I just try to feel it, to get a sense
of it and not think about it so much.
Christ, I sound like FM radio. Relax. Still, you need
aesthetic guidelines to put it in social perspective.
I don't know. I mean, I guess
you must be sort of late.
You know, I've got to get
there and begin whining soon.
Are you busy Friday night?
Me? Oh, no.
Oh, I'm sorry, I have something.
What about Saturday night?
Nothing. No, no.
You're very popular, I can see.
- I know.
- You have plague?
I meet a lot of jerks.
I meet a lot of jerks, too.
I'm thinking about
getting some cats.
Wait a second! No, no! Oh, shoot!
Saturday night,
I'm going to sing.
You're going to sing?
You sing? No kidding!
- This is my first time.
- Really? Where?
I'd like to come.
- I'm interested. -
No, no. I'm just a-
I'm auditioning at this
club. It's my first time.
That's okay, 'cause I know
exactly what that's like.
You're going to like nightclubs.
They're really a lot of fun.
It had to be you
I wandered around
And finally found
This somebody who
Could make me be true
Could make me be blue
And even be glad
Just to be sad
Thinking of you
I was awful! I'm so
ashamed! I can't sing.
So the audience
was a tad restless.
What do you mean, "a tad
restless"? My God, they hated me!
No, they didn't. You
have a wonderful voice.
- I'm going to quit.
- I'm not going to let you.
- You have a great voice.
- Do you think so, really?
- Yeah! It's terrific.
- I never even took a lesson either.
- Listen, give me a kiss.
- Really?
Why not? Because we're
just going to go home later.
There's going to be all that
tension. We've never kissed before.
I'll never know when
to make the right move.
We'll kiss now and get it over
with, and then we'll go eat. Okay?
We'll digest our food better.
Okay? Now we can digest our food.
Corned beef, please.
I'm having pastrami
on white bread...
with mayonnaise,
tomatoes and lettuce.
So, your second wife left you.
Were you depressed about that?
Nothing that a few
mega-vitamins couldn't cure.
- Your first wife, Allison.
- She was nice.
That was my fault.
I was too crazy.
That was so nice! That was nice.
As Balzac said, "There
goes another novel. "
You were great.
Oh, yeah? Yeah?
- Yeah, I'm wrecked.
- You're wrecked.
I mean it. I'll never
play the piano again.
It was, I don't know. You
really thought it was good?
Good? Yes. No, that was the most
fun I've had without laughing.
Here, you want some?
No, I don't use any
major hallucinogenics.
I took a puff about five
years ago at a party...
and tried to take my
pants off over my head.
I don't do it very often.
It just sort of relaxes me.
- You won't believe
this, but- - What?
I'm going to buy
you these books...
because I think you should read
them instead of that cat book.
That's pretty serious stuff.
I'm obsessed with death, I think.
It's a big subject with me. I
have a pessimistic view of life.
You should know this about
me if we're going to go out.
I feel that life is divided up
into the horrible and the miserable.
Those are the two categories.
The horrible would be like terminal
cases and blind people, cripples.
I don't know how they get
through life. It's amazing to me.
And the miserable
is everyone else.
So when you go through life, be
thankful that you're miserable.
You're very lucky
to be miserable.
Look at that guy. There's
Mr. Miami Beach in the pink.
He's just come back from
the gin rummy finals.
He placed third.
Look at these guys. That's hilarious.
They're back from Fire Island.
They're sort of giving
it a chance romantically.
- Italian, right?
- Him? He's the Mafia.
Linen supply business or
cement and contracting.
Oh, gee, mess up
my moustache wax.
There's the winner of the
Truman Capote look-alike contest.
You are unbelievably
sexy. Yes, you are.
You know what you are? You're
polymorphously perverse.
What does that mean? I
don't know what that is.
You're exceptional in bed...
because you get pleasure in every
part of your body when I touch it.
Like the tip of your nose, and if I
stroke your teeth or your knee caps...
you certainly get excited.
You know what? I
like you, I really do.
But do you love me?
That's the key question.
I know you've only
known me a short while.
I think that's sort of
- Yeah, yeah.
Do you love me?
Love is too weak a word for what
- I "lurve" you.
I "loave" you. I "luff"
you, with two "f"s.
Of course I do.
Don't you think I do?
I don't know.
What do you mean? You're not going to
give up your own apartment, are you?
- Of course.
- But why?
I'm moving in with
you, that's why.
- But you have a nice apartment.
- I have a tiny apartment.
- I know it's small.
- And it's got bad plumbing and bugs.
Granted, it has bad plumbing and bugs.
You say that like it's a negative.
Bugs are-
- Entomology is a rapidly growing field.
- You don't want me to live with you.
- I don't? Whose idea was it?
- Mine.
It was yours, actually.
But I approved it immediately.
You think I talked
you into something.
No. We live together, we sleep
together, we eat together.
Jesus, you don't want it to
be like we're married, do you?
- How is it any different?
- Because you keep your own apartment.
It's there. We don't have
to go to it, deal with it...
but it's like a free-floating life raft
that we know that we're not married.
That little apartment
is $400 a month, Alvy.
- That place is $400 a month?
- Yes, it is.
It's got bad plumbing
and bugs. Jesus.
My accountant will write it off as
a tax deduction. I'll pay for it.
You don't think I'm smart
enough to be serious about.
Don't be ridiculous.
Then why are you always pushing me to
take college courses like I was dumb?
Adult education is
a wonderful thing!
You meet a lot of interesting
professors. It's stimulating.
Does this sound like a good
course: "Modern American Poetry"?
Or, let's see...
maybe I should take
"Introduction to the Novel. "
Just don't take any course
where they make you read Beowulf.
What?
What do you think? Should we go
to that party in South Hampton?
No, don't be silly. What
do we need other people for?
We should just turn out the lights
and play hide the "salam" or something.
Well, I'm going to
get a cigarette, okay?
Grass, right? The illusion that it makes
a white woman more like Billie Holiday.
- Have you ever made love high?
- Me? No.
If I have grass or alcohol,
I get unbearably wonderful.
I get too wonderful for words.
I don't know why you have to
get high every time we make love.
It relaxes me.
You have to be artificially
relaxed before we can go to bed?
What's the difference, anyway?
I'll give you a shot of Sodium
Pentothal. You can sleep through it.
Look who's talking! You've been
seeing a psychiatrist for 15 years.
You should smoke some of this.
You'd be off the couch in no time.
- Come on, you don't need that.
- What are you doing?
- No, Alvy, please?
- You can live without it once.
Wait, I got a great idea.
Hang in there for a second. I
got a little erotic artifact...
that I brought up from the city,
which I think is going to be perfect.
There. Create a little
old New Orleans essence.
Now we can go about
our business...
and even develop
photographs if we want to.
- Is something wrong?
- No, why?
I don't know. It's
like you're removed.
No, I'm fine.
Really?
I don't know. You
seem sort of distant.
Let's just do it, all right?
Was it my imagination or are you
just going through the motions?
Alvy, do you remember
where I put my drawing pad?
Because while you two are doing
that, I'm going to do some drawing.
That's what I call removed!
You have my body.
But I want the whole thing!
I need grass.
It ruins it for me
if you have grass.
I'm like a comedian, so if I get
a laugh from a person who's high...
it doesn't count, 'cause
they're always laughing.
Were you always funny?
Is this an interview? We're
supposed to be making love.
This guy is naturally funny.
I think he can write for you.
Yeah, yeah. Hey, kid, he
tells me you're really good.
Let me explain how I work.
You can tell off the bat...
that I don't look like a funny
guy like some of the guys.
You know they're going to tell you
their stories, you're going to fall down.
But I gotta be really talented.
Material's got to be sensational for me.
I work
- I'm kind of classy. Know what I mean?
Let me explain. I'll
open with an opening song.
The music will start.
I walk out. Place looks
wonderful from here
You folks look
And seeing you there
With a smile on your face
Makes me shout This
must be the place
I stop, and then I open with some
jokes. That's where I need you.
I'll say, "I just got back from
Canada. They speak a lot of French.
The only word to know is 'John Dark. '
It means the light's out in the bathroom.
- I met a big lumberjack. "
- Jesus, this guy's pathetic.
Look at him mincing around.
Boy, thinks he's real cute.
You want to throw up.
If only I had the nerve
to do my own jokes.
I don't know how much longer I can
keep this smile frozen on my face.
I'm in the wrong
business. I know it.
"But, cherie...
what will I do with this, eh?"
He says, "Oh, Marie,
sometime you make me so mad!"
They scream at that. Write me
something like that, will you?
Kind of a French
number. Can you do it?
Where am I? I have
to reorient myself.
This is the University
of Wisconsin, right?
Because I'm always tense
when I'm playing a college.
I have a bad history with colleges.
I went to New York University.
And I was thrown out of
NYU my freshman year...
for cheating on my
metaphysics final.
I looked within the soul of
the boy sitting next to me.
My mother, an emotionally high-strung
woman, locked herself in the bathroom...
and took an overdose
of mah-jongg tiles.
I was depressed at that
time. I was in analysis.
I was suicidal, as a matter of
fact, and would have killed myself...
but I was in analysis
with a strict Freudian.
And if you kill yourself, they make
you pay for the sessions you miss.
Alvy, you were just
great. I'm not kidding.
College audiences are wonderful.
You know what? I think I'm starting
to get more of the references, too.
Are you? The 12:00 show is
completely different than the 9:00.
I'm looking forward to tomorrow. It'll
be nice. You'll meet Mother and Father.
They'll hate me immediately.
No, I don't think they're going
to hate you at all. Contrary.
It's Easter. We'll sit down and
eat. I think they'll really like you.
It's a nice ham this year, Mom.
Grammy always does
such a good job.
Great sauce.
It is. It's dynamite ham.
We went to the swap meet.
Annie, Gram and I. Got
some nice picture frames.
We really had a good time.
Ann tells us you've been seeing
a psychiatrist for 15 years.
Yes. I'm making
excellent progress.
Soon, when I lie down on his couch,
I won't have to wear the lobster bib.
- Duane and I went to the boat basin.
- We caulked hulls all day.
And Randolph Hunt
was drunk as usual.
That Randolph Hunt! You
remember Randy Hunt, Annie.
- He was in the choir with you.
- Oh, yes.
I can't believe this family.
Annie's mother is
really beautiful.
And they're talking swap
meets and boat basins.
The old lady at the end of the
table is a classic Jew-hater.
They really look American, healthy,
like they never get sick or anything.
Nothing like my family. The
two are like oil and water.
Ah, let him drop dead.
Who needs his business?
- His wife has diabetes.
- Diabetes? Is that an excuse?
The man is 50 years old and
doesn't have a substantial job.
Is that a reason to
steal from your partner?
You don't know what
you're talking about.
Defend him!
Pass the brisket.
Mo Moskowitz. He had a coronary.
You don't say!
How do you plan to spend
the holidays, Mrs. Singer?
- We fast.
- Fast?
No food. You know,
to atone for our sins.
What sins? I don't understand.
Neither do we.
Hi, Duane. How's it going?
- This is my room.
- Oh, yeah? It's terrific.
Can I confess something?
I tell you this, because, as an
artist, I think you'll understand.
Sometimes when I'm driving...
on the road at night...
I see two headlights
coming toward me, fast.
I have this impulse to
turn the wheel quickly...
head-on into the oncoming car.
I can anticipate the explosion.
The sound of shattering glass.
The flames rising out
of the flowing gasoline.
Right.
I have to go now, Duane, because
I'm due back on the planet Earth.
Don't let it be so long now.
- Look up Uncle Billy, promise.
- He is adorable.
- You'll take them to the airport now?
- No. Duane can.
- I haven't finished my drink.
- Yes, Duane is. I'll be right-
You followed me.
I can't believe it!
- I didn't follow you.
- You followed me!
Because I was walking a block behind
staring at you? That's not following.
- What's your definition of "following"?
- Following is different. I was spying.
Do you realize how
paranoid you are?
Paranoid? I'm looking at you, and
you've got your arms around another guy.
That is the worst
kind of paranoid!
I didn't start out spying. I thought I'd
surprise you, pick you up after school.
You wanted to keep the relationship
flexible, remember? It's your phrase.
You're having an affair
with your college professor!
That jerk that teaches that crap course,
"Contemporary Crisis in Western Man. "
"Existential Motifs in Russian
Literature. " You're really close.
What's the difference? It's
all mental masturbation.
Now we're getting to a subject
you know something about.
Don't knock masturbation.
It's sex with someone I love.
We're not having an affair. He's
married. He happens to think I'm neat.
Are you 12 years old? That's one
of your Chippewa Falls expressions.
Who cares?
Next he'll find you're keen and peachy.
Then he'll have his hand on your ass.
You've had hostility towards
David ever since I mentioned him.
- You call your teacher David?
- It's his name.
It's a Biblical name, right?
Does he call you Bathsheba?
Alvy, you're the one who never
wanted to make a real commitment.
You don't think I'm smart enough.
We had that argument last month...
or don't you remember that day?
- I'm home!
- How'd it go?
It was really weird, but
she's a very nice woman.
I didn't have to lie on the
couch. She had me sitting up.
I told her about the family
and my feelings towards men...
and my relationship
with my brother.
Then she mentioned penis
envy. Do you know about that?
I'm one of the few males
who suffers from that. Go on.
She said I was guilty about my
impulses towards marriage and children.
Then, I remembered, when I was a kid, I
accidentally saw my parents making love.
All this happened the
first hour? That's amazing.
I've been going for 15 years.
I don't have nothing like that.
I told her my dream,
and then I cried.
You cried. I've never once
cried. That's fantastic to me.
I whine. I sit and I whine.
In my dream, Frank Sinatra is
holding this pillow across my face...
and I can't breathe.
He's strangling me.
Sure, because he's a singer, and
you're a singer. It's perfect.
You're trying to suffocate
yourself. It makes perfect sense.
That's a perfect
analytic insight.
She said your name
was Alvy Singer.
- What do you mean, me?
- Yeah, you.
Because in the dream, I
break Sinatra's glasses.
You never said Sinatra had glasses.
Are you saying I'm suffocating you?
God, I did this really
terrible thing to him...
because then when he sang, it
was in this real high-pitch voice.
- What'd the doctor say?
- I should come five times a week.
I don't think I mind analysis at all.
The question is, will it change my wife?
- Will it change your wife?
- Will it change my life?
- But you said "wife. "
- No, I said "life. "
- No, you said "wife. "
- "Life!" I said "life. "
She said "wife. " You heard that,
because you were there. I'm not crazy.
Then I told her I didn't think
you'd ever take me seriously...
because you don't
think I'm smart enough.
Why do you bring that up? Because I
encourage you to take adult education?
It's a wonderful thing. You meet
wonderful, interesting professors.
Adult education is junk. The
professors are phony. How can you do it?
I don't care what you say about
David. He's a fine teacher.
And why are you following me around?
We should call this relationship quits.
That's fine. That's great. I
don't know what I did wrong.
Somewhere she cooled off to
me. Is it something that I did?
It's never something you do.
That's how people are. Love fades.
Love fades. God, that's
a depressing thought.
I have to ask you a question.
Don't go any further.
With your wife, in bed, does she need
some kind of artificial stimulation...
like marijuana?
We use a large vibrating egg.
A large vibrating egg.
I ask a psychopath, I get
that kind of answer. Jesus!
You look like a
very happy couple.
- Are you?
- Yeah.
How do you account for it?
I'm very shallow and empty,
and I have no ideas...
and nothing interesting to say.
- I'm exactly the same way.
- I see.
That's interesting. So you've
managed to work out something?
Right.
Thanks for talking to me.
Even as a kid, I went for the wrong
women. I think that's my problem.
When my mother took
me to see Snow White...
everyone fell in love with Snow
White, and I fell for the wicked queen.
- We never have any fun anymore.
- How can you say that?
Why not? You're always leaning
on me to improve myself.
You're upset. You must
be getting your period.
I don't get a period. I'm a cartoon
character. Can't I be upset sometimes?
Max, forget about Annie. I
know lots of women you can date.
I don't want to go
out with other women.
Max, I've got a girl for you. You are going to
love her. She's a reporter for Rolling Stone.
There are more people here
to see the Maharishi...
than there were to
see the Dylan concert.
I covered the Dylan concert,
which gave me chills.
Especially when he sang, "She
takes just like a woman...
and she makes love
just like a woman.
Yes, she does.
And she aches just
like a woman...
but she breaks just
like a little girl. "
Up to that, the most
charismatic event I covered...
was Mick's birthday when the
Stones played Madison Square Garden.
That's just great.
You catch Dylan?
No, I couldn't make it.
My raccoon had hepatitis.
You have a raccoon?
A few.
The only word for this
is "transplendent. "
- It's transplendent.
- I can think of another word.
He's God. I mean,
this man is God.
He's got millions of followers,
who would crawl across the world...
just to touch the
hem of his garment.
It must be a tremendous hem.
- I'm a Rosicrucian myself.
- Are you?
I can't get with any religion that
advertises in Popular Mechanics. Look.
There's God coming
out of the men's room.
It's unbelievably transplendent!
I was at the Stones' concert when
they killed that guy. Remember?
Were you? I was at an
Alice Cooper thing...
where six people were rushed
to the hospital with bad vibes.
I hope you don't mind that
I took so long to finish.
Me? No. Don't be silly.
I'm starting to get some
feeling back in my jaw now.
Sex with you is really
a Kafkaesque experience.
Thank you.
I mean that as a compliment.
I think there's too much
burden placed on the orgasm...
to make up for
empty areas in life.
Who said that?
I don't know. I think it may
have been Leopold and Loeb.
Hello.
No. What's the matter?
You sound terrible.
No, what-
Sure, I-
What kind of emergency?
No, stay there. I'll
come over right now.
Just stay there.
I'll come right over.
It's me. Open up. Are you okay?
What's the matter?
Are you all right?
There's a spider in the bathroom.
- What?
- There's a big spider in the bathroom.
You got me here at 3:00 a. m.
'cause a spider's in the bathroom?
You know how I am about insects. I can't
sleep with that thing crawling around.
Kill it! What's wrong with you?
Don't you have Raid in the house?
I told you a thousand times
to keep a lot of insect spray.
- You never know who will crawl over.
- I know.
And a first aid kit
and fire extinguisher.
Give me a magazine,
'cause I'm a little tired.
You make fun of me, but
I'm prepared for anything.
An emergency, a tidal
wave, an earthquake.
What is this? Did you
go to a rock concert?
Yeah.
Really? How'd you like it?
Was it heavy? Did it
achieve total "heavyosity"?
It was just great!
I've got an idea. Call the guy
who took you to the rock concert...
and he can come
and kill the spider.
I called you. You
want to help me or not?
Since when do you read the National
Review? What are you turning into?
I like to get all points of view.
Wonderful. Get William F.
Buckley to kill the spider.
You're a little
hostile, you know that?
Not only that, you
look thin and tired.
It's 3:00 in the morning.
You got me out of bed.
I ran over. I couldn't get a
taxi. You said it was an emergency.
I ran up the stairs.
I was more attractive
when the evening began.
Are you going with a
right-wing rock-and-roll star?
Would you like a glass
of chocolate milk?
- What am I, your son? I came over
for- - I've got the good chocolate.
- Where's the spider?
- It's in the bathroom.
Don't squish it. After it's dead,
flush it down the toilet, okay?
I've been killing spiders
since I was 30. Okay?
It's a very big spider. A lot
of trouble. There's two of 'em.
I didn't think it was that
big, but it's a major spider.
- You got a broom or snow shovel?
- I left it at your house. I'm sorry.
What are you doing?
There's a spider in your
bathroom the size of a Buick.
- You got black soap?
- It's for my complexion.
Are you joining a minstrel show?
Don't worry.
I did it. I killed them
both. What's the matter?
What are you sad about? Did you want
me to capture and rehabilitate 'em?
- Don't go, please.
- What do you mean?
What's the matter? Are
you expecting termites?
What's the matter?
I don't know. I miss you.
Jesus! Really?
- Alvy?
- What?
Was there somebody in your
room when I called you?
- What do you mean?
- I mean, I thought I heard a voice.
I had the radio on. I'm
sorry, it was the television.
Let's never break up again.
I don't want to be apart.
I think we're both much too
mature for something like that.
Living together hasn't
been so bad, has it?
For me it's been
terrific. You know?
Better than either
of my marriages.
There's something different about
you. I don't know what, but it's great.
I think, if you let me, I
could help you have more fun.
I know it's hard. Yeah.
What if we go away this weekend?
Why don't we get Rob, and the three
of us would drive into Brooklyn?
We could show you the old
neighborhood. That'd be fun for you.
Yeah, I'd love it.
God, it's a great day!
Watch the road!
You'll total the car!
I've never been to Brooklyn.
- I can't wait to see the neighborhood.
- The neighborhood will be great.
- We could show her the schoolyard.
- I was a great athlete. Tell her.
I was all-schoolyard.
They threw him a football
once. He tried to dribble it.
I used to lose my glasses a lot.
Look! That's my old house.
That's where I used to live.
Holy cow!
You're lucky. Where I used to live
is now a pornographic equipment store.
I had some very
good memories there.
What good memories, your mother
and father fighting all the time?
And over the most
ridiculous things.
- You fired the cleaning woman?
- She was stealing!
But she's colored. The
colored have enough trouble!
- She was going through my purse.
- They're persecuted enough.
- Who's persecuting? She stole!
- So? We can afford it.
How can we afford it, on your
pay? What if she steals more?
She's a colored woman from
Harlem. She has no money.
She has a right to steal from us.
Who can she steal from if not from us?
- You're both crazy.
- They can't hear you.
Leo, I married a fool!
What's that?
That's the welcome home party,
1945, for my cousin Herbie.
Look. That over
there is Joey Nichols.
He was my father's friend. He was
always bothering me when I was a kid.
Joey Nichols. See? Nickels.
See? Nickels. You see? Nickels.
You can always remember my name.
Just think of Joey Five-Cents.
That's me. Joey Five-Cents.
What an asshole.
The one who killed me the most
was my mother's sister, Tessie.
I was always the sister
with good common sense...
but Tessie was always
the one with personality.
When she was younger, they
all wanted to marry Tessie.
Do you believe Tessie
had the personality?
- She's the life of the ghetto no doubt.
- She was once a great beauty.
Tessie, they say you were
the sister with personality.
I was a great beauty!
- How did this personality come about?
- I was very charming.
There were many men
interested in you?
I was quite a lively dancer.
It's very hard to believe.
I had a really good day. It was
a fine way to spend my birthday.
- Your birthday isn't until tomorrow.
- But it's real close.
But no presents until midnight.
Happy birthday.
What is this? Is this a
present? Are you kidding?
Yeah. Why don't you try it on?
- This is more like a present for you.
- It'll add ten years to our sex life.
Yeah. Forget it.
Here's a real present.
- What is this anyway?
- Check it out.
You knew I wanted this.
God, it's terrific!
Just put on the watch and
that thing. It'll be perfect.
Seems like
Old times
Having you
To walk with
Seems like
Old times
Having you to walk with
And it's still a thrill
Just to have my arms
Around you
Still the thrill
That it was the day
I found you
Seems like
Old times
Dinner dates and flowers
Staying up all hours
Making dreams come true
Doing things we used
To do
Seems like
Old times
Here with
You
Thank you.
You were sensational.
I told you if you stuck to
it, you would be great and-
You were sensational.
Yeah, they were a
terrific audience.
It makes it easy for
me, because I can be-
Excuse me. Hi, I'm Tony Lacey.
- We wanted to say we enjoyed your set.
- Yeah? Really?
I thought it was very
musical. I liked it a lot.
That's really nice. Thanks a lot.
Are you recording?
Are you with any label?
Me? No, not at all.
I'd like to talk to you about
that sometime if you get a chance.
Possibly working together.
That's nice. This is Alvy
Singer. Do you know Alvy?
I don't, but I know your
work. I'm a big fan of yours.
This is Shawn, Bob and Petronia.
We're going back to the Pierre...
and we're going to meet Jack
and Angelica for a drink.
If you'd like to come,
we'd love to have you.
We can sit and
talk. Not a big deal.
Just relax, be very mellow.
Remember we had that thing?
What thing?
Remember we discussed that thing?
Oh, the thing! Oh,
the thing. Yeah.
Well, if it's inconvenient,
that's fine, too.
We'll do it another time. If you're
on the coast, we'll get together there.
It was a wonderful set.
I really enjoyed it.
Nice to have met you. Good night.
What's the matter? You
want to go to that party?
I don't know. I
thought it might be fun.
It would be nice to
meet some new people.
I don't think I could take a mellow
evening. I don't respond well to mellow.
If I get too mellow,
I ripen and rot.
- It's not good
for my- - All right.
You don't want to go to the
party. What do you want to do?
That day in Brooklyn was the last
day I remember having a good time.
- We never have any laughs anymore.
- I've been moody and dissatisfied.
- How often do you sleep together?
- Do you have sex often?
Hardly ever. Maybe
three times a week.
Constantly. I'd say three times a week.
Like the other night, Alvy wanted sex.
She would not sleep
with me the other night.
I don't know. Six months ago I would
have done it just to please him.
I tried everything.
I put on soft music
and my red light bulb.
Since our discussions here, I feel
I have a right to my own feelings.
I think you would have been happy,
because I really asserted myself.
The incredible thing is, I'm
paying for her analysis...
she's making progress,
and I'm getting screwed.
I feel so guilty, because
Alvy is paying for it.
So I feel guilty if I
don't sleep with him.
But if I do sleep with him, it's like
I'm going against my own feelings.
- I'm not making any progress.
- I can't win.
Sometimes I think I
should live with a woman.
I don't believe it. You
guys have never snorted coke?
I always wanted to try,
but Alvy's very down on it.
Don't put it on me. I don't want to
put a wad of white powder in my nose.
There's the nasal membrane.
- You never want to try anything new.
- How can you say that?
I said you, I and that girl from
acting class should sleep together.
- That's sick.
- I know it's sick, but it's new.
- You didn't say it couldn't be sick.
- Come on, Alvy.
- Do your body a favor. Try it.
- It'll be fun.
I'm sure it's fun, 'cause the Incas
did it. They were a million laughs.
For your own experience.
You want to write. Why not?
It's great stuff, Alvy. A friend
just brought it in from California.
I didn't tell you. We're
going to California next week.
It's really a
thrill, as you know.
On my agent's advice, I sold out
and am going to do a TV appearance.
That's not it at all.
Alvy's giving an award on TV.
You act like you're
violating a moral issue.
It's so phony. We have to leave New
York during Christmas. It kills me.
Listen, while you're in California,
could you score some coke for me?
Sure, be glad to. I'll just put
it in the hollow heel on my boot.
- How much is this stuff?
- About $2,000 an ounce.
Really? And what
is the kick of it?
I've never been so relaxed as I
have been since I moved out here.
I want you to see my house.
I live next to Hugh Hefner.
And the women are like in Playboy,
but they can move their arms and legs.
I can't get over that this
is really Beverly Hills.
The architecture is really consistent.
There's French next to Spanish...
next to Tudor next to Japanese.
It's so clean out here.
Because they don't throw garbage
away. They make it into TV shows.
- Give us a break. It's Christmas.
- Can you believe this is Christmas?
It was snowing and
really gray in New York.
Nice. Santa Claus
will have sun stroke.
Max, there's no crime,
there's no mugging.
There's no economic crime...
but there's ritual,
religious cult murders.
There's wheat-germ
killers out here.
While you're out here, I
want you to see my TV show.
And we're invited to
a big Christmas party.
Charlie, give me
a good laugh here.
A little bigger.
Do you realize how
immoral this all is?
I've got a hit series.
But you're adding fake laughs.
Give me a tremendous laugh here.
We do the show live in
front of an audience.
But nobody laughs, because
the jokes aren't funny.
That's why this
machine is dynamite.
Give me a medium chuckle here...
and then a big hand.
Is there booing on that?
I don't feel well.
- What's the matter?
- I got very dizzy.
- I feel dizzy.
- Sit down.
Jesus.
You all right? You
want to lie down?
No. My stomach felt
queasy all morning.
How about a ginger ale?
No. Maybe I'd better lie down.
Try to get some of this
down. It's just plain chicken.
No, I can't eat
this. I'm nauseous.
If you could get me something to
get me through the next two hours.
I have to go to Burbank and
give out an award on a TV show.
There's nothing wrong with
you as far as I can tell.
You have no fever, no
symptoms of anything serious.
- You haven't eaten pork or shellfish.
- Excuse me. I'm sorry, Doctor.
Alvy, that was the show. Everything
is fine. They found a replacement.
They're going to
tape without you.
Jesus! Now I don't
get to do the TV show?
- I can't find any reason for this.
- Nothing at all?
- I could get a lab man up here.
- Hand me the salt, please.
Perhaps it would be better if
we took him to the hospital.
The hospital?
- There's no other way to diagnose him.
- This is not bad, actually.
Don't tell me we're going to have
to walk from the car to the house?
My feet haven't touched pavement
since I reached Los Angeles.
I'll take a meeting with you if
you'll take a meeting with Freddy.
I took a meeting with Freddy.
Freddy took a meeting with Charlie.
- You take a meeting with him.
- All the good meetings are taken.
Right now it's only a notion.
I think I can get money to make it into
a concept, then turn it into an idea.
Like this house, Max?
Even wrote a road map to
get us to the bathroom.
You should have told me
it was Tony Lacey's party.
What difference does that make?
I think he has a thing for Annie.
- No. He goes with that girl over there.
- Where?
- The one with the VPL.
- VPL?
Visible panty line.
She's gorgeous.
She's a ten. That's great for you,
'cause you're used to two's, aren't you?
There are no two's.
You're used to the kind with shopping
bags walking through Central Park...
with the surgical
masks on, muttering.
How do you like this couple? They look
like they're from Masters and Johnson.
Intensive care ward. My God!
- I think she's giving me the eye.
- If she comes over, my brain will mush.
You're Alvy Singer, right?
Didn't we meet at EST?
No, I was never to EST.
- Then how can you criticize it?
- He didn't say anything.
I came to get some shock therapy,
but there was an energy crisis.
- He's my food taster. Have you two met?
- How do you do?
- Do you taste for poisoned food?
- Yeah, he's great.
You guys are wearing white.
It must be in the stars.
- Uri Geller must be on the premises.
- We're going to operate together.
In about six weeks we
could cut the whole album.
I don't know. This
is strange to me.
You can stay here. Use the
whole wing in this house.
- Stay here?
- Really. Why are you smiling?
Not only is he a great agent,
but he really gives good leading.
This is a great house: saunas,
Jacuzzis, three tennis courts.
You know who the original owners
were? Nelson Eddy then Legs Diamond.
- Then you know who lived here?
- Trigger.
Charlie Chaplin, right
before his un-American thing.
- But you guys are still New Yorkers.
- Yeah, I love it there.
I used to live there for
years, but it's so dirty now.
- I'm into garbage. It's my thing.
- This is a nice screening room.
There's another
thing about New York.
If you want to see a movie,
you have to stand on line.
It could be freezing
or raining. And here-
We saw Grand lllusion
here last night.
That's a great film if you're
high. It's really funny.
Come and see our bedroom. We
did a fantastic thing up there.
I'm cool.
It's wonderful. They eat
and watch movies all day.
And gradually you get old and die. It's
important to make an effort sometimes.
- Do you think his girlfriend's pretty?
- She's great looking.
A little on the androgynous side.
I forgot my mantra.
That was fun.
I don't think
California is bad at all.
It's a drag coming home.
A lot of beautiful women.
It was fun to flirt.
I have to face facts.
I adore Alvy, but our relationship
doesn't seem to work anymore.
I'll have the usual trouble
with Annie in bed tonight.
Why do I need this?
If only I had the nerve to break
up, but it would really hurt him.
If only I didn't feel guilty
asking Annie to move out.
It'd probably wreck her,
but I should be honest.
Alvy, let's face it.
I don't think our
relationship is working.
I know. A relationship
is like a shark:
It has to constantly
move forward or it dies.
And I think what we've got
on our hands is a dead shark.
- Whose Catcher in the Rye is this?
- If it has my name on it...
I guess it's mine.
You wrote your name in all my books,
'cause you knew this day would come.
You wanted to break up
just as much as I do.
No question. I think we're
doing the mature thing.
Look. All the books on
death and dying are yours.
And all the poetry
books are mine.
Denial of Death. This is
the first book I got you.
Remember that day?
I feel like there's a
great weight off my back.
Thanks, honey.
I mean, no. I think it's important
for us to explore new relationships.
There's no question about that, because
we've given this a more than fair shot.
My analyst thinks this
move is key for me.
And I trust her, because
my analyst recommended her.
Why should I put you through
all my moods and hang-ups anyway?
You know what the beauty part is? We
can always come back together again.
- There's no problem.
- Exactly.
I don't think many couples could handle
this, break up and remain friends.
This button is mine. Remember?
These are yours. "Impeach
Eisenhower. " "Impeach Nixon. "
"Impeach Lyndon Johnson.
" "Impeach Ronald Reagan. "
I miss Annie. I made
a terrible mistake.
She's living in Los
Angeles with Tony Lacey.
If she is, then the hell with her. If
she likes that lifestyle, let her stay.
- He's a jerk for one thing.
- He graduated Harvard.
Harvard makes mistakes,
too. Kissinger taught there.
Don't tell me you're jealous?
Yeah. Jealous? A
little bit. Like Medea.
Can I show you something? I
found this in the apartment.
Black soap. She used to wash her
face 800 times a day with black soap.
Don't ask me why.
Why don't you go
out with other women?
I tried, but it's
very depressing.
This always happens to
me. Quick! Get a broom!
What are you making
such a big deal about?
They're only lobsters.
- You're adult. You can pick up lobsters.
- I'm not myself since I quit smoking.
- When did you quit?
- Sixteen years ago.
- What do you mean?
- Mean?
You stopped smoking 16 years
ago. Is that what you said?
I don't understand.
Are you joking or what?
Central Park's turning green.
I saw that lunatic we used to
see with the pinwheel hat...
and the roller-skates.
Listen, I want you
to come back here.
Well, then I'm going to
come out there and get you.
What do you mean, where am
I? Where do you think I am?
I'm at the Los Angeles
airport. I flew in.
I flew in to see you.
Can we not debate this
on the telephone...
because I've got a temperature...
and I'm getting my chronic
Los Angeles nausea again.
Wherever you want to
meet. I don't care.
I'll drive in. I rented a car.
I'm driving.
What, is that such a
miracle? I'm driving myself.
I'm going to have
the alfalfa sprouts...
and a plate of mashed yeast.
You look pretty.
No, I just lost a little
weight, that's all.
Well, you look nice.
I think we should get married.
Come on.
Why, you want to live out here?
It's like living in Munchkinland.
What do you mean? It's
perfectly fine out here.
Tony's very nice.
I meet people, go to
parties and play tennis.
That's a very big step for me.
I'm able to enjoy people more.
You're not going to
come back to New York?
What's so great about New York? It's
a dying city. You read Death in Venice.
You didn't read Death in Venice
until I bought it for you.
That's right. You only gave me books
with the word "death" in the title.
Because it's an important issue.
You're incapable of
enjoying life. You know that?
You're like New York City.
You're just this person.
You're like this
island unto yourself.
I can't enjoy anything
unless everybody is.
If one guy is starving someplace,
it puts a crimp in my evening.
Do you want to get married?
No. We're friends.
I want to remain friends.
Check please.
You're mad, aren't you?
Yes, of course I'm mad, because
you love me. I know that.
I can't say that that's true
at this point in my life.
I really can't say that's true.
You know how wonderful you are.
You're the reason I got out of my
room, that I was able to sing...
and get more in touch with
my feelings and all that crap.
Listen, listen.
So what are you up to?
The usual. I'm trying to
write. I'm working on a play.
Are you saying you're not
coming back to New York with me?
No. Look. I gotta go.
What do you mean? I flew
3,000 miles to see you.
Air miles. Do you know what
that does to my stomach?
If you must know, it's
a hectic time for Tony.
- The Grammys are tonight.
- The what?
The Grammys. He's got a lot
of records up for awards.
They give awards for that
music? I thought just ear plugs.
Just forget it. Let's just
forget the conversation.
They do nothing but give out
awards. I can't believe it.
Greatest Fascist
Dictator: Adolph Hitler.
I know what you're going to
say. I'm not a great driver.
- I have some problems with- -
May I see your license, please?
Just don't get angry.
I have my license
here. It's a rented car.
Don't give me your life's story.
Just pick up the license.
You have to ask nicely, because
I've had a rough day. My girlfriend-
Just give me the license, please.
Since you put it that way,
it's hard for me to refuse.
I have a terrific
problem with authority.
It's not your fault.
Don't take it personal.
So long, fellows. Keep in touch.
Imagine my surprise
when I got your call.
Yeah. I had the feeling
I got you at a bad moment.
I heard high-pitched squealing.
Twins, Max.
Sixteen-year-olds.
Can you imagine the mathematical
possibilities of that?
You're an actor. You should be
doing Shakespeare in the park.
I did Shakespeare in
the park. I got mugged.
I was playing Richard ll. Two guys
with leather jackets stole my leotard.
Are we driving through plutonium?
Keeps out the alpha
rays. You don't get old.
You're a thinking person. How
can you choose this lifestyle?
What is so great about New York?
It's a dying city. You
read Death in Venice.
You didn't read Death in
Venice until I gave it to you.
You only give me books with
the word "death" in the title.
- It's an important issue.
- You're incapable of enjoying life.
You're like New York.
You're an island.
Okay. If that's all that we've been
through together means to you...
it's better if we just said
good-bye, once and for all.
It's funny.
After all the serious talks
and passionate moments...
that it ends here, in a health
food restaurant on Sunset Boulevard.
Good-bye, Sally.
Wait. I'm going to go with you.
I love you.
What do you want?
It was my first play.
You know how you're always trying to
get things to come out perfect in art...
because it's real
difficult in life.
Interestingly, however, I
did run into Annie again.
It was on the Upper
West Side of Manhattan.
She had moved back to New York. She
was living in Soho with some guy.
When I met her, she was dragging him
in to see The Sorrow and the Pity...
which I counted as
a personal triumph.
Annie and I had lunch
sometime after that...
and just kicked around old times.
Just to have my arms
Around you
Still the thrill
That it was the day
I found you
Seems like
Old times
Dinner dates and flowers
After that, it got late
and we both had to go.
But it was great
seeing Annie again.
I realize what a
terrific person she was...
and how much fun it
was just knowing her.
And I thought of that old joke.
This guy goes to a psychiatrist
and says, "Doc, my brother's crazy.
He thinks he's a chicken. "
The doctor says, "Why
don't you turn him in?"
The guy says, "I would,
but I need the eggs. "
Well, I guess that's, now,
how I feel about relationships.
They're totally irrational,
crazy and absurd.
But I guess we keep
going through it...
because most of us need the eggs.